Guide to the Reginald Moore Houston area community activism collection, 2000-2016 MS 653
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Reginald Moore Houston area community activism collection
2000-2016
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Moore, Reginald
MS 653
2 Linear Feet 2 boxes
5 Gigabytes Audio and video files from public testimony
This collection represents the community activism efforts of Mr. Reginald Moore, which has often taken the form of researching topics as represented in newspaper accounts, requesting government records on the topics, and corresponding with officials and engaging in public testimony. Private Sector Initiatives / Home Savers initiative - church based effort which Mr. Moore either led or was just deeply involved in to get the black community out participating in assisting fellow African Americans in repairing their homes via volunteer efforts. (Holman Street) Houston Community College - misappropriation of funds Housing and Urban Development, later renamed as Housing and Community Development, funding shortages. Mr. Moore involved in seeking government records and providing public testimony. Prison reform - experience as correctional officer, research in newspapers, sharing ideas and opinions in public forums such as call-in radio shows (not documented in this collection) and corresponding with public officials regarding legislation for eVerification as a tool to facilitate employment of ex-convicts. Wards and churches in Houston -- research in newspapers, public testimony (in collection, including Antioch Church video testimony at City Council) Yates High School public testimony lobbying to save the building, Houston City Council 2/09/2016 video Additional methods of activism which are not specifically documented in this collection include frequent radio show call-ins regarding issues relevant to the AFrican American community, for example with the Rev. Jesse Jackson's show "Keep Hope Alive" and Houston radio station Magic 102.1.
Biographical / Historical
Reginald Moore, of Sugar Land, Texas, is an historian and has a certification in Community Economic Development from the College of Biblical Studies. He is also a community activist, and has a particular interest in prison reform and prison re-entry into society. He served as a correctional officer in the Texas Department of Corrections, 1985-1988. Mr. Moore worked in the Beauford H. Jester I and III Units, a prison farm located in unincorporated Fort Bend County, Texas. Jester I Farm was the first built by the state at this site, and was known as the Old Harlem Farm. Although convict leasing as a practice is believed to have begun informally in 1872, the State of Texas sanctioned the contract to lease the penal system to the private firm of Ed H. Cunningham and L.A. Ellis (Cunningham and Ellis) in 1878. In 1883, the land and system reverted from private to state control. While working at this site, Mr. Moore became interested in the history of the Flanagan House (former warden's house) and then in the Central Unit of the prison. Over time, this interest grew and became a major research area for Mr. Moore, who went on to found and chair the Texas Slave Descendants' Society(TSDS) in the early 2000's. Through the TSDS and on his own, Mr. Moore, has worked to gain recognition for the past abuses associated with Sugar Land's convict leasing system. Mr. Moore serves as a member of the RIP Guardian program for the Imperial Prison Cemetery.
Additionally, Mr. Moore has worked to bring attention to other topics such as modern day prison reform, mis-use of public funds, and preservation of Houston's historically African American wards and churches.
Resources of interest: CNN film "American Jail" https://www.cnn.com/shows/american-jail-film, access July 3, 2018
Scope and Contents
This collection represents the community activism efforts of Mr. Reginald Moore, which has often taken the form of researching topics as represented in newspaper accounts, requesting government records on the topics, and corresponding with officials and engaging in public testimony.
Private Sector Initiatives / Home Savers initiative - church based effort which Mr. Moore either led or was just deeply involved in to get the black community out participating in assisting fellow African Americans in repairing their homes via volunteer efforts. (Holman Street)
Houston Community College - misappropriation of funds
Housing and Urban Development, later renamed as Housing and Community Development, funding shortages. Mr. Moore involved in seeking government records and providing public testimony.
Prison reform - experience as correctional officer, research in newspapers, sharing ideas and opinions in public forums such as call-in radio shows (not documented in this collection) and corresponding with public officials regarding legislation for eVerification as a tool to facilitate employment of ex-convicts.
Wards and churches in Houston -- research in newspapers, public testimony (in collection, including Antioch Church video testimony at City Council)
Yates High School public testimony lobbying to save the building, Houston City Council 2/09/2016 video
Additional methods of activism which are not specifically documented in this collection include frequent radio show call-ins regarding issues relevant to the AFrican American community, for example with the Rev. Jesse Jackson's show "Keep Hope Alive" and Houston radio station Magic 102.1.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mr. Reginald Moore.
Reginald Moore can be contacted by phone.
To contact him, please provide your phone number to the staff at the Woodson Research Center, at woodson@rice.edu or 713-348-2586. The staff will provide your request to Mr. Moore, in accordance with our donor privacy policy. Thank you very much.
Related Materials
Reginald Moore featured as caller on C-Span television show Dec. 27, 2017, "Angela J. Davis on Race and Criminal Justice Reform," online at https://www.c-span.org/video/?438867-3/washington-journal-angela-j-davis-discusses-race-criminal-justice-reform.
Index Terms
Subjects
Prisoners and prisons; African Americans; Slavery; Civil rights
Document Types
notes; letters (correspondence); clippings (information artifacts); photographs; minutes (administrative records)
- Series I: Private Sector Initiatives / Home Savers initiative
  - Correspondence to and from Moore regarding service projects, and newsclippings, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - VHS video (9:58 duration) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Color photographs of service projects repairing homes and service award ceremonies (including Moore), 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Series II: Houston Community College misappropriation of funds
  - Clippings, notes and reports, 2014-2015 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Public meeting minutes, 2013-2015 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - HCC real estate deeds and correspondence, 2008-2015 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series III: Housing and Urban Development planning and funding shortage in Houston
  - Correspondence on waste, fraud, and abuse, 2008-2016 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Recordings of Moore's public testimony on HUD funding shortages, at Houston City Council and Houston Commissioners Court, 2013-2015 (DVD video format) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newsclippings regarding HUD funding shortages, 2008-2012 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Houston planning publications, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Prison reform and reentry
  - Prison re-entry and eVerification as a way to facilitate employment, correspondence with city and county officials, and newsclippings, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Prison reform newsclippings, general (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series V: Houston wards and churches
  - Houston wards and churches: newsclippings and a history of Mt. Carmel Missionary Baptist Church (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- Series VI: Other areas of interest
  - Houston sidewalk and transportation issues, 2013-2015 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Juneteenth in Houston / complaints to Alief YMCA, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Port of Houston / Rosewood Cemetery in Galveston (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Prairie View A&M Interscholastic League correspondence regarding Hall of Fame, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Texas history textbook updates, 2008-2014 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Yates High School / Houston Independent School District (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    General
    Includes correspondence regarding support for the Maritime program at Yates High School and other alumni concerns, as well as 1977-1979 yearbook.
  - General Black history newsclippings (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series VII: Audio and video advocacy and testimony
  - Audio recorder files of Moore's calls in to radio and tv shows, and recordings of meetings (MS0653aip_001), 2009-2014
    Includes a listing of the files of these 95 audio files. Shows include Tom Hartman Show, CSPAN, Democracy Now, Brunch with Bernie, and others. Meetings include Moore's homeowners association, possibly Black Panthers meeting, church services.
    Conditions Governing Access
    This digital material is stored in the Woodson Research Center's nearline environment. Contact woodson@rice.edu for access, referencing this identifier number: MS0653aip_001.
  - Audio recordings of Reginald Moore in HUD overspending, Yates High School Maritime Academy, Longshoremen event, and C-SPAN clip on Hurricane Harvey money (MS0653aip_002), circa 2016-2018
    This digital material is stored in the Woodson Research Center's nearline environment. Contact woodson@rice.edu for access, referencing this identifier number: MS0653aip_002.
  - Video recording of public testimony by Reginald Moore on HUD misappropriation of funds, City of Houston (MS0653aip_003)